Guide to the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) at Duke University Records, circa 1923-1985 UA.31.04.0013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) at Duke University records
circa 1923-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
YWCA at Duke University
UA.31.04.0013
7.2 Linear Feet
A chapter of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) was established at Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) in 1917. In 1925, a new constitution was drafted and the chapter became the YWCA at Duke University. The records of the Duke University YWCA span the years 1923 to 1985, with the bulk dating between 1930 and 1970, and include reports, printed matter, correspondence, sermons, clippings, and financial records.
6,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) at Duke University Records were received by the University Archives as transfers between 1973-1983.
Biographical/Historical note
A chapter of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) was established at Trinity College in 1917. In part, it was formed by Trinity women in order to assist with the war effort (World War I). In 1925, a new constitution was drafted and the chapter became the Duke University YWCA. In 1970, the chapter merged with the Duke University YMCA to form the Duke University YM-YWCA.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Duke University YWCA span the years 1923 to 1985, with the bulk dating between 1930 and 1970, and include reports, printed matter, correspondence, sermons, clippings, and financial records. Prominent subjects include race relations, annual activities of YWCA, community service, Edgemont Community and sermons preached at Duke Chapel during the 1960s.
Collection includes publications such as 1931 issue of "Opportunity: Journal of Negro Life," published by the National Urban League and 1931 issue of "Black Justice," published by the American Civil Liberties Union.
Related Material
Young Men's--Young Women's Christian Association at Duke University Records, 1968-1979
Duke University Archives
Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) at Duke University Records, 1920-1969
Duke University Archives
Minister to the University (Dean of the Chapel) Records, 1940-1984
Duke University Archives
Maude Brown Scrapbook, 1924-1937
Duke University Archives
Odessa Massey Scrapbook, 1924-1928
Duke University Archives
Blanche H. Clark Scrapbook, 1923-1928
Duke University Archives
Alice Craven Scrapbook, 1915-1924
Duke University Archives
Sermons; Edgemont Community Center (Durham, N.C.); Duke University. Chapel; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, customs, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; YWCA of the U.S.A.; YWCA at Duke University; YWCA at Duke University
- Administrative Records, circa 1924-1985
  - Constitution, circa pre-1925-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - By-laws, 1946-1948, 1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1929-1936 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1957-1960 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1961-1965 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Chapter Cabinet Minutes, 1936-1940 (Box 2)
  - Chapter Cabinet Minutes, 1945-1948 (Box 2)
  - Chapter Cabinet Minutes, 1953-1954, circa 1959, circa 1966 (Box 2)
  - Chapter Committee Minutes, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1954 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1966 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Inter-Racial Committee, circa 1924-1934, undated (Box 3)
  - Inter-Racial Committee, printed matter, circa 1930s, undated (Box 3)
  - Chapter Committees, circa 1940-1961 (Box 3)
  - Committee Plans, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Resident Secretary, circa 1937-1946 (Box 3)
  - Advisory Board, 1936-1966 (Box 3)
  - Agendas, 1936-1966 (Box 3)
  - Freshman and Sophomore Commissions, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
  - Freshman Week, 1945-1970 (Box 3)
  - Freshman Y Council, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Receipt Books, 1938-1946 (Box 4)
  - Secretary's Book, 1932-1935 (Box 4)
  - Treasurer's Records, 1936-1946 (Box 4)
  - Recognition Services, 1927-1966 (Box 4)
  - Retreats, 1939-1961 (Box 4)
  - Activities, 1937-1961 (Box 4)
  - Members, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Flyers, 1961, circa 1975-1985 (Box 4)
  - Conference, Meetings and Programs, circa 1938-1952 (Box 5)
  - Dating at Duke (social relationships), 1938 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1930-1968 (Box 5)
- Printed Matter, circa 1927-1970, undated
  - YWCA Newsletter, nos. 1-3, circa 1954-1955, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Y and Wherefore [newsletter], 1947-1948 (Box 5)
  - Live Y'er [newsletter], 1956-1958 (Box 5)
  - North Carolina Community Schools [newsletter], 1939 Jan. 15-Apr. 15 (Box 5)
  - Humanity, 1966 Oct.-1969 Apr. (Box 5)
  - Wind and Chaff, 1966 Nov.-1967 Nov. (Box 5)
  - Richard C.D. Lyon's Labor Lives and Lyon's Labor Lettres, circa 1938-1939 (Box 5)
  - Federation News Sheet [bulletin], 1941 Sept.-Nov. (Box 5)
  - Brochures, circa 1930-1970 (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets and Booklets, undated, 1927, 1930-1949 (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets and Booklets, 1950-1954 (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets and Booklets, 1955-1959 (Box 6)
  - YWCA Cabinet Handbook, 1948-1949, 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - YWCA Cabinet Handbook, 1953-1954, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, 1930-1939 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950-1959 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1970 (Box 7)
- General YWCA, YM-YWCA, 1932-1970
  - General, 1933-1949 (Box 7)
  - General, 1950-1964 (Box 7)
  - General, 1965-1970, undated (Box 7)
  - National Student Council, 1932-1940 (Box 7)
  - National Student Council, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - National Student Council, 1944-1952 (Box 8)
  - National YWCA Minutes, 1950-1952, 1968 (Box 8)
  - YM-YWCA Constitution, 1970-1971 (Box 8)
  - YM-YWCA Cabinet, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - YM-YWCA Advisory Board, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - Abortion, 1963-1969 (Box 8)
  - Vietnam, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Clergy and Laymen, Vietnam, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
- Edgemont Community Center, circa 1941-1970
  - By-laws, 1955-1956, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Reports, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
  - Reports, 1957-1963 (Box 9)
  - Reports, 1964-1969 (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1942-1967 (Box 9)
  - Board, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Living-Learning Project, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Financial, 1943-1966 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1941-1968 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous, circa 1930-1970, undated
  - Duke MOBE, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Duke University Christian Council, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Duke University Religious Council, 1957-1963 (Box 10)
  - Duke University Religious Council, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Community Concerns Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Interfaith Fellowship Committee, 1958, 1963 (Box 10)
  - North Carolina Intercollegiate Council for Human Rights, 1965 (Box 10)
  - National Association of College and University Chaplains, 1962-1963 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Materials, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Materials, circa 1930-1949 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Materials, 1950-1964 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Materials, 1965-1970 (Box 11)
- Sermons, 1923-1971, undated
  - Writings, Sermons, 1923 (Box 11)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1950s (Box 11)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1962 (Box 11)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1963 (Box 11)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1964 (Box 12)
  - Writings, Sermons, 1965-1966, 1970-1971 (Box 12)
  - Writings, Sermons, undated (Box 12)
  - Writings, Sermons, undated (Box 12)
- Oversize, 1926-1956
  - The Chronicle (Box 13)
    - Scoop Extra, 1939 Apr. 4 (Box 13)
    - Extra Edition, 1940 Oct. 16 (Box 13)
  - Flyers-Join the Duke 'Y' includes calendar, 1952-1956 (Box 13)
  - Onward, 7 February 1926 (Box 13)
  - Second Bulletin on Interracial Student Conference to be held in Durham, circa 1938 (Box 13)
  - Welcome flyers including map of Duke campus, overview of the YWCA, and a general information sheet tailored to residents of Epworth Inn, circa 1950 (Box 13)
  - Y and Wherefore, 1946 Oct. (Box 13)